so this is a suitor from the
nikkei we've done this before this one
we've done this before this one
oh
just do it again
because i will teach you a dharma
exposition on union and disengagement
i'll just go with the man's description
a man because attends internally to his
masculine faculty his masculine
comportment his masculine appearance
his masculine aspect his masculine
desire his masculine voice
his masculine ornamentation
he becomes excited by these and takes
delight in them
excited by them and taking delight in
them he attends externally to a woman's
feminine faculty to the
counterpart and so
he becomes excited by these and takes
delight in them
excited by them taking delight in them
he desires union externally
and he also desires the pleasure and joy
that arise on account of such union
beings who are delighted with their
masculinity enter upon union with women
it is in this way that the ma
that a man does not transcend his
masculinity this is how union comes about
and how does this engagement come about
well let's talk about the union
well the first thing you will notice
there is
so it's not about denying
masculinity or femininity by the way the
same thing applies to the feminine the
same we would have said the same thing
for a woman who attends to her
femininity she gets attracted to the
counterpart externally
or whatever he might represent the
counterpart but the point is
but the point is
it's not about denying
the nature of the body you are paired
with so it's not about denying the
so it's not about denying the
masculinity or denying the femininity
it's about
carelessly becoming dependent upon the
pleasures of the masculine body
of the masculine body
or the pleasures of the feminine body
which then results in seeking the
external counterpart
so the whole point is to
become developed
in regard to your own body as the other
suitors would say
not about oh there is you know there is
no gender there is this masculinity is
just an illusion
yeah in a sense there is no gender in a
sense that is yours that it can be owned
by you
but factually the body is so
it is such
with such hormones with such
predispositions which such height and
shape and so on and that's not the
problem the problem is that there is a
basis of pleasure that can arise on
account of the body
and your mind is not developed in regard
to that
so when the prospect of pleasure makes
itself apparent
you are accepting the body you are
accepting the ownership you are
carelessly identifying and taking up the ownership
identifying and taking up the ownership
of whatever you're paired with in this
case with the masculine aspects and then
as a result of it you seek the pleasure
even further outside which is you know
the counterpart for it
and as a result of that you seek the
union and become deployed dependent on
the pleasure of the union and everything
else you know the burdens they come with
it all of that you take on just because
you were not developed in regards to
that initial pleasure that you are
paired with prospect of pleasure that
you are paired with your body
so it's not about denying the masculine
or denying the feminine or even denying
that the attraction
that you might have developed on account
of the body before it's about overcoming
the pressure of it
that can be done first by not acting out
of it and then by truly understanding
the nature of it the unknown ability of
it
and and
disengaging yourself
with the union with that pleasure
um so for that your mind needs to have
developed out of that pressure towards
pleasure that's felt physically that
central itch and so on
that masculine aspect that is
pleasurable well yes yeah like the
masculine the body whether masculine or
feminine whatever it is
is
it is a basis of a certain type of
physical pleasure
that it's for a masculine for a man it's
on the basis of his masculinity for for
a woman it's on the basis of her
femininity either way
either way
that provides the basis for that craving
for physical pleasure so that why is it
pleasure not enough
so that
which
so it's not really a pleasure it's the
prospect prospect of patients yeah
why is it not enough what do you think
why would not be enough say the prospect
of pleasure why is that not enough it's
a good question why is it not enough in
itself because
it's not in my control
it's not mine
no no why is it not enough though
why by default mind that's not developed
why would that mind seek the external
counterpart why wouldn't the pleasure of
masculinity feminine be enough in itself
why would you spill outside and seek the
union with the external
why why is that
it's because of a view
it's because of the assumption of where
where the pleasure of central kind is
it's because of the assumption that it's
in the external sense objects not on the
level of your body in the same sense the
people assume
that they are accessing seeing
perceiving owning the external objects
and not their senses seeing perceiving
and owning
so in other words your senses your
masculinity your body or femininity is
invisible to you because you've been
carelessly cultivating actions towards
that pleasure out there
which is also factual but it's actually
secondary to the pleasure of the body
its sense objects are secondary to the
existence of the fatigue of your senses
and the only reason you don't see that
is because you keep assuming you keep
holding the view that that's first and
this is second
this gets attracted to that because of
that
and thus whatever's here is seen a
second and it that's why it's seen as
and it that's why it's seen as
insufficient that's why you're not
developed in regard to the body
because you assume the wrong order and
the wrong order prevents the development
but if you say well it doesn't matter
how far
out i reach and seek
i reach and seek
the experience of pleasure is bound
within the framework of these senses
so the only way i can know the external
world it's on account of these senses
knowing the external world which means
for me the assumption that i had of the
external world it's pretty much actually
inconceivable if you start thinking
about it clearly
you realize oh there was a complete
misconception all you're assuming is the internal of
all you're assuming is the internal of
your senses and that's all you can have
but you will not even be able to
to reach like the even the basic level
of this clarity if you are still acting
on account of the assumption of external
coming first
and your body your desire the pressure
second it's just a response to the
impulse so for as long as you keep that picture
so for as long as you keep that picture
perverted
there is no development there is no
uprooting of sensuality there is no
abandonment of masculinity or femininity
and that still but what uh vanderbilt
islander said i think to the vanguiser
is it
we said oh please help me your mind is
infected with passion i can't see the
way out and he said it's due to the
perversion of perception that you still
remain attracted to it
perversion of the order literally it's
due to putting that which second is
first so what is first
so what is first
what is first is the framework of your
senses there is no outside of it you're
fully enclosed with it you start
recognizing that you're gonna start
feeling deep anxiety because you realize
you're utterly utterly
enclosed trapped within yourself
and any notion of the external world any
notion of the external pleasure is
not it's not like oh it's not real it's
real but it's also enclosed with you
it's within
so that's that like oh buried alive in a
sense where we spoke before and that's
why people
there are underlying tendencies that
just push you
in the direction of sensuality
because if you resist it you're left
with deep
fear and pain
and and terror
because your assumption is of the
external world and suddenly you see
doesn't matter the extent of the
universe you travel as the buddha would
say it's within this body
and when you actually take that in a
realistic sense it's quite frightening
for a mind that's not developed
for a mind it's still dependent on the
pleasures of the external kind you can't
reach beyond your sense you can't step
it's inconceivable your thoughts cannot
even feather the outside of it the only
way to do so is to misconceive it and
through that misconception
that misconception exists as such
so that's what would have meant the form
finds the footing
in the existence through your
misconceiving so it exists as external
so it exists as external
although it can't
by not knowing that that's how it exists
for you
and that's the the fundamental
perversion of the order
sensuality is that bhava is that and so
on
so seeing that your senses come first
and you can only see that if you have
not been acting out of them out of the
pressure if you've been withdrawing from that
if you've been withdrawing from that
pressuring addiction of scratching the
edge with the external means
and then you start saying oh this is the
reason outside of this
so even your thoughts are outside it's
not that you stop having them you just
see them correctly as within this
so the clearer that becomes
the the
the lesser
so to speak the lesser
amount of perversion you are living
on your day-to-day basis
to the point where the perversion would
have been completely
sort of eradicated
you cannot
doesn't matter what you see smell hair
taste touch you think
your mind cannot fall back into the
assumption of the wrong order because
the right order has been understood
thoroughly sufficiently enough that the
perversion cannot take place that's when
you know your mind is free from
karmababa mind is free from central
craving intentional being
because the the pla the pleasure of the
external kind was not the centrality it
was the perversion of the order
that his sensuality was there
and that's exactly what this that sort
of describes through not being developed
in that which is first which for a man
is the masculine framework of the body
and the senses
for a woman it's the feminine framework
of the body of the senses
you start spilling outside assuming
outside big time even more dependent on
the outside
by not being developed means by not not
seeing it clearly not having practice
sensory strain sufficiently enough not
having developed your mind in regard to
the the the pressure
the the pressure
not having endured it patiently long
enough having been acting out of it
having been
keeping the precepts as a means of
external duty not as a means of direct
development of your mind by not acting
out of the pressure of the current sense
all of that means not developed in
regard to your own masculinity or
femininity
means not being able to seat
as as impersonal as a nature
so he he gives in delights in his
masculine pressure the masculine pressure or you
pressure the masculine pressure or you
could just say he takes his masculine
his pressure of masculinity he takes it
for granted
by default his mind is already outside
attracted to those things even if he's
avoiding them
because of taking the pressure for
granted as mine as belonging to me
as mine as belonging to me
not having a mind developed in regard to
that pressure means pressure will
overwhelm the mind mind will not
overwhelm the pressure so by default
that will put you outside but if you
have sustained sufficiently enough not
acting out of that pressure and
discerning it but discerning it guarding
of the sense doors not just do i just
keep the precepts because it's my duty
but you recognize that ah
intentionally choosing to abstain from thinking about
choosing to abstain from thinking about
things that would be taking up the
pressure intentionally sort of keeping an eye on
intentionally sort of keeping an eye on
your actions on your decisions on your
choices on the responsibility behind
they will make you not spill out towards
the external world you are becoming
aware basically of
uh
what is it that you've been doing
they've been perpetuating your
dependence on the pressure and the
external world which is taking the
pressure for granted
as yours
so you start allowing it to be
not trying to get rid of it
so that you can endure it correctly
not act out of it correctly
god just sends those in regard to it
correctly means you're taking up responsibility
means you're taking up responsibility
for it and you're not taking it for
granted anymore
means you will be able to eventually see
it as not yours
not like oh now i need to see it is not
mine by not acting out of it by guarding
a sense in regard to it but taking
responsibility for it by allowing it to
endure not trying to get rid of it all
of these are ways of practicing of not
mine and with that sufficiently cultivated
and with that sufficiently cultivated
then that whole perverted order that
dependent on account of taking up the
pressure is mine
would have faded
or would have diminished sufficiently
for you to see that it has diminished
so there's that
there's an idea
which is i have lust
for women
so
now i must contemplate
the disgusting nature of a woman's body
see that's now the problem with that is
you took it as a
as a duty as a sense of an external duty
when lust is present i must do this
no when last is present
you must first acknowledge it active act
yeah lust is present in your mind you
need to recognize the mind of lust as
mind of lust
not like mind of lust i do this mind of
non-lust i do that either way i will try
to not be aware of myself because it's
too unpleasant
the mind of lust is there that needs to
be endured
so the mind of lust is there i must not
act out of it
and if you are jumping into practice of
a subaru immediately means you're acting
out of it you're not allowing it to be
for what it is the phenomenon of lust
the mind affected with love you're
trying to get rid of it
and which is exactly the the motion of
sensuality lust is present you jump into the
lust is present you jump into the
centrality to get rid of that painful
itch so now you learn that's bad so what do i
so now you learn that's bad so what do i
do last is present you jump into acting
out to get rid of that painful itch
so that's the the two extremes that
people end up going towards by not
understanding the middle way
you are a scratch rate or try to deny
the edge so people's practice of asuba
often falls on the level of just trying
to deny the itch
and that's not the asuba
that's not uprooting of the last they're
just managing managing of it
and not even that well because it
it's going to come back and the asuba
will lose effectiveness the more you do
it
rooted in wrong wrong reasons
so the mind of lust is present the first
thing you know is like okay i should not
act out of this
but i should do a subaru well i should
do a subaru when the mind of lust is not
present because otherwise i'm doing a subaru
because otherwise i'm doing a subaru
rooted in lust
i'm trying to deny the lust why would i
try to deny the last because i don't
want to endure it oh well there you go
the first step of patient endurance is
what you don't even want to do so all
the subsequent steps you might be doing
are on the basis of your silhouette
parameters of avoiding responsibility
for the first step of enduring it
not trying to get rid of it and again and again
you
so you have the underlying there's the
underlying tendency towards lust
so lust is not exactly active now
in that active sense
so but i can still see that i am liable
to lust so now i can do that
exactly so there's no mind of lust
actively present
but am i free from last well you know
okay so now i should contemplate and try
to basically redefine the framework of
attractive by seeing it as unattractive
so create a broader context of
unattractive because it is there
it's just you haven't been looking at
those aspects
but you can only do that rightly when
the mind is properly established
so when you're not rooted in trying to
get rid of the lazy avoidance of
endurance yeah you properly establish means being
yeah you properly establish means being
able to patiently enjoy being able to
patient you have not acted out of it
now you are not gripped by lust okay let
me now contemplate
contemplate this suba contemplate the
unattractive contemplate the danger all
these things
then when the last comes back you
wouldn't need to or what do i do now
because if you sufficiently contemplated
the nature of that which is lustful it's
going to be that implicit in that
lust so that which was lustful comes now
with a even richer background of
unattractive because that's what you've
been cultivating so that's when we're
like rewriting the significance of
things so through that
so through that
significance of lust now there is the
also further significance of
danger unattractive not worthy to be
avoided to be to be not acted out of
and the clearer that broader context
becomes the uh the more impossible would it be
the uh the more impossible would it be
for you
to put that superficial aspect of lust
first and ignore all the context as
second in other words your mind is becoming
in other words your mind is becoming
more and more imperturbable
in regard to the lust because the
context is becoming established and it's
not moving it doesn't matter how
forceful how quick how
how how how
sharp the the last might be the context
remains first
that's like mine has settled in the
right order and it cannot tip over
anymore
just to that
specific contemplation with the person
might say well i'll contemplate the
disgusting nature of another person's
body but it's it's better to
but it's it's better to
look at this i mean it's okay you can
think that but well first as i said if
you're doing it on the basis of mind
that's not the fact that we lasted in
time you can do it internally externally
it doesn't matter
it doesn't matter you can do it
externally you can go to other bodies
your body will be included with that if
you're doing internally other bodies
will be included in that if it's not
done on the basis of lust and trying to
avoid the endurance of the mind affected
with lust or any unwholesome hindrance
so it says how does one just
practice disengagement
basically you don't delight in note
in your masculine
aspect don't take it for granted
and then there is the pressure the
possibilities that your masculine form
is offering you possibilities of
pleasure yeah
yeah
you you you need to practice
um
non-zeo non-interest towards those
non-interest towards those
don't take them up for granted but
actually start contemplating and
regarding them as parallels
so that's basically using your body
for the sake of
gaining the external pleasures
so which you can never gain which you
can have again because it's already a
perverted order but if you don't
understand that then you would be
established based upon
based upon
uh pretty much dependent upon the form
that you have which you know is
masculine or feminine
and by that means you you took for
granted you took the ownership of it and
that's you know the beautification the
the the
the anxiety that you get in regard to
the form if you get sick the sense is
failing all of that is on that level
that means oh you already took it for
granted so what you need to do is you
can't just all i will now untake it
i'll just let go of it
it's not a matter of direct choice but
what you can do is first stop acting out
of
the form
being taken for granted
so stop acting out of towards external
pleasures stop practicing sense restraint endure
stop practicing sense restraint endure
your senses endure the pressure exactly
endure their own patiga
with and try to see it as impersonal as
possible um um
and then
if you become
more accustomed which is what samadhi is
stop stop resisting basically being
unmoved because you're becoming more
accustomed because you endured it
sufficiently enough
so if you become more accustomed to the
interior of your senses which is what
you the only thing you ever had
there is no exterior to your own
experience because there will be a contradiction in
because there will be a contradiction in
terms
you become accustomed to it you stop
resisting it
then you can see it as a thing there
you can see it as a thing there
doesn't mean oh i need to become
feminine in order to overcome my
masculine or a feminine person needs to
become masculine no that's just you
acting out of whatever you have and
trying to deny it by with the opposite
no all you need to do is stop taking for
granted and stop assuming the ownership
of it then any pleasure there was
depending on that will fade away that
doesn't mean that you would lose the
perception of that you still have male
body or a female body
but you will not delight in the
masculine aspects nor the feminine
aspects nor would you be saddened or
distraught if something happens to them
so yeah so this is what this is
interesting was saying is a being
so
discerning that pressure of the body
there discerning that interior which you
cannot step outside
and then and then eventually seeing that
as a thing arisen yeah and
on its own that's not yours yeah you you
will see it as much yeah if you are
accustomed to it sufficiently enough
you'll be able to see it as just being
there so this that that brings me to this
so this that that brings me to this
other suitor
i'll put the suitors in the comments
it says confinements
and this deva it's called confinement
the suit and this davis
said this verse
the sage
the withdrawn chief bull
the buddha who awakened to jhana the one
of broad wisdom
has found the opening amid confinement
what friend has the buddha the blessed
one spoken of as confinement and what as
the achievement of an opening in the
midst of confinement
and just briefly the blessed one friend
has spoken of these five objects of
central pleasure as confinement
and it goes on what is non-confinement
i mean the the opening what is the
opening amidst that confinement so the
opening is not finding another direction
of your senses
or denial of the senses the opening is
removal of the ownership of that which
confines you
complete
complete basically non-appropriation
which is begins with first gen that's
what keeps you
inside the interior or
the interior or
not that i don't say it keeps you that
you go outside of it but what do you
mean the open the opening emits confinement
the open the opening emits confinement
is that
it's the escape of the confinement
that's what it means
not the opening
yeah like the opening commits
confinement or what is that opening it's
not like you find the opening through
the aggregates
from which you can sort of slip out of
samsara no it's like you are confined by
everything that appears
the ultimate confinement
so what is then the opening of amidst
that what is the escape amidst all force
fully being buried alive it's removal of
the ownership of that situation in its
entirety and that's when the first jhana there is
and that's when the first jhana there is
no sense of i am i'm entering the first
gen but it's not that there is no sense
of the five senses there is but there is
no ownership of it there is thinking and
pondering but the traces of ownership
have been completely removed on every
level thus nobody is confined there's no
thus nobody is confined there's no
confinement
because in order for something to be
confined you need that which confines and that
you need that which confines and that
one which is confined
the assumed sense of self
so complete removal of the ownership and
conceit is the utter that that that
the subtlest of the openings
so to speak the escape
amidst everything that confines
and that's what it says that the first
genre is that opening that escape from
its establishment upon the first escape
pretty much but then he sees that there
is a confinement
there yes but now you're getting
abstract like uh
like uh
if a person develops first genre they'll
understand the true okasa the true uh
opening among sambada confinement the
polyworld and then the principle of other genres
and then the principle of other genres
will become apparent but if somebody
tries to out the opening the confinement
of the confinement
none of that becomes applicable now
because it's just taken as an abstract
sense so so
again
the opening the escape from the
confinement from that which confines
which is the ownership is the
removal it's the uprooting it's the
fading away of ownership and conceit in
regards to the senses and the sense
objects and the pleasures you've been
dependent upon
that's why first jana is enough
as the suitors would say you don't need
second and third and fourth
first jhana if you establish your mind
upon that first escape first level of
orcasa first level of
opening amid confinement
amid confinement
and spend sufficient amount of time in
it
you will have completely uprooted any
loss towards anything that was confining
before and and experience this passion towards
and and experience this passion towards
it but yes theoretically speaking one
who is establishing the first jhana can
then start thinking about oh is there a
more refined okasa more refined escape
even in regard to this which you know
from the point of view of the second
jhana the first jana is very coarse
from the point of view the third genre
the second ghana is very coarse
so you use that principle
to remove the ownership
because you know jhana in itself does
not necessarily bring the full uprooting
of the sense of i am and sense of mind
for that you need wisdom
that's why again theoretically a person
could have janas without you know having
fully uprooted
their underlying tendencies
that's it so here i am with
the pressure of the body there's a
pressure of the body and i want to
satisfy it
i want to get rid of that pressure
i want to feel pleasure
i don't want to feel this depression
why is that and why burden to me well
what is the burden
it's confinement
you are confined
by this discomfort by the pressure so
what do you do you try to get rid of the
pressure by
letting it outside
so that's why you will not find the true
opening amidst confinement because you
keep acting out of confinement towards
the assumed opening
so the sense pleasures of the external
kind are the assumed relief of the
pressure here
and that's why people are so
psychologically dependent on scratching
the age
because that's the only form of orcas
the only form of release
from confinement that they know
there's no release there it's not a
release that is the reason for your
confinement your assumption of wrong
release
and the more you go you try that
well the more yeah exactly the more
confined you become
the more burdened by your dependence on
sexuality you become
it's like the more you that's why it's
important to realize that this needs to
be lived on the level of enduring the
pressure not acting out of it calming
your mind within it
so withdrawal from the dependence on the
pleasure of the assumed external kind is
the prerequisite for that pleasure of
ghana that that the genuine release of
the burden of the debt of crossing the
desert all the similarities the buddha
gave for the pleasure of first ghana
withdrawing from it's withdrawing from
the unwholesome
withdrawing from the wrong order that
you've been assuming
that's your work
and then the release will occur as a
result of it of the right kind that
would be the true opening amidst the
confinement but people don't want to
deal with the confinement don't want to
deal with the pressure don't want to
deal with enduring it they want a
technique they will get them the
experience of pleasure that they will
then take to bijana and then assume that
all this work has been done on account
of this special meditation pleasure that
they had
and as i said many times that's exactly
mirroring principle of the centrality
that you've been tracing and acting out
of now just instead of that you're
watching your nostrils or whatever else
but you're still seeking for that
pleasant thing to be your escape
no the escape is found by not becoming
not being not maintaining the dependence
upon the wrong order
and then the pleasure of jhana will
happen having been quite withdrawn from
central pleasures he abides and dwells
and experience pleasure of withdrawal
and then he mind enters and abides in
the first genres that's how suitors
describe it not
not having been withdrawn still being
pressured by sensuality he gets a
technique he enters jhana and all this
just falls off and senses disappear and
it's a magical experience
yeah well good luck with that one
as soon as you wake up from that boom
yeah it needs to be practical and if you
think okay so the second channel the
third ghana again that's what would have
said it's like a cow that hasn't even
established itself upon the first rock
it stepped on
plan yeah started planning to step on
the second one and falls between the two
so refrain from thinking about
perception neither perception nor
perception and the basis of infinite
space and everything else until you have
been quite withdrawn from sensuality and
have experienced at least that first
basic orcasa of of first genre of
complete relinquishment of ownership
and and subsiding of unwholesome states
when there is no more basis for the
perversion of the order
that's why john is so wholesome